<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a pistel or letter sent to Gilbard Potter in the tyme when he was in prison for speakinge on our most true quenes part the Lady Mary before he had his eares cut of. The. xiii of Julye.</title>
            <author>Poor Pratte.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1553</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100408</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836249</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836249</idno>
            <idno type="VID">508</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09927)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 508)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1358:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a pistel or letter sent to Gilbard Potter in the tyme when he was in prison for speakinge on our most true quenes part the Lady Mary before he had his eares cut of. The. xiii of Julye.</title>
                  <author>Poor Pratte.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [R. Jugge for] Hewghe Singelton],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London in Temstrete ouer agaynste the stiliardes, at the signe of the dobbel hood :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.Liii. the firste of August [1553]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The name of the author, Poore Pratte, is a pseudonym--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name and place of publication from colophon. Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Potter, Gilbard.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Mary I, 1553-1558 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:508:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:508:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:508:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:508:2"/>
The copie of a piſtel or letter ſent to Gilbard Potter in the tyme when he was in priſon, for ſpeakinge on our moſt true quenes part the Lady Mary before he had his eares cut of.</p>
            <p>The .xiij. of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si deus nobiſcum, quis contra nos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno. M. D. Liij. the firſte of Auguſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:508:3"/>
            <head>Poore Pratte, vnto his frend Gilbard Potter, the mooſt fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and trew louer of quene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doth him ſalute with many ſalutations. S. P. D.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas thou haſte of late ſhowed thy ſelfe (moſt faithful Gilbard) to be a true ſubiecte to Mary quene of England, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by wordes, but by deedes, and for the farther triall of thy true heart towardes her did offer thy bodye to be ſlayne in her quarell, and offered vp thy ſelfe into the handes of the ragged beare moſt ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke, with whome is nether mer cy, pitie, nor compaſſion, but his in dignation preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t death. Thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis (Gilbarde) is faythfull. Thy heart is true. Thy loue is ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te towardes her grace. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:508:3"/>
you did promis me faythfullye (when I laſt viſited thee in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to be torne with wild horſes, thou wouldeſt not denye Marye oure Quene, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche thou tofore dyd ſaye, no denial ſhalbe found in thee, ſo ſtyll do thou continue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame mynde, haue a reſpect of thy conſcience. Feare not to ſaye the truth, if thou dye, thou ſhalt die in the ryght, <hi>pugna propatria,</hi> fighte for thy countrey (ſayeth the Philoſo pher). For as it ſhalbe to thi great honour and prayſe in this world &amp; in heauen to dye in her graces quarel, &amp; in the defence of thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trey, ſo wold it be to the vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, both of thy body &amp; ſoule to do the contrarye. But (o thou true Gilbard) ſtande ſtiflye in her cauſe, &amp; do thou according to thy laſt promis made me (as I do not doubt but thou wilt) then wil god kepe thee and preſerue thee. If
<pb facs="tcp:508:4"/>
thou ſhuld dye, thou ſhalt die inno cent, ſo ſhal you be aſſured to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the euerlaſtyng kyngdom of heauen. If you fortune to lyue, then ſhal it be alſo acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted praiſe to thee. And fully perſwade with thy ſelfe, that her grace wil conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy faythful &amp; true heart (as ſhe hath iuſte occaſion). For who could haue bene more faythfuller then thou haſte bene? What man coulde haue ſhowed him ſelfe bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in her graces cauſe, then thou haſt ſhowed? Or who dyd ſo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antlye in the proclamation tyme, when Iane was publiſhed quene (vnworthy as ſhe was) &amp; more to blame, I may ſay to thee, are ſome of the conſenters therunto. Ther were thouſandes more then thy ſelfe, yet durſt they not (ſuche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fragility &amp; weakenes of the fleſh) once moue their lippes to ſpeake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, whiche thou did ſpeake. Thou
<pb facs="tcp:508:4"/>
offereſt thy ſelfe amongſt the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of people to fight agaynſte them all in her quarel, and for her honour dyd not feare to runne v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the poynt of the ſwordes. O faythful ſubiect, O true hearte to Mary our Quene, I can not but wryte of the conding prayſe that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> deſerueſt for thys thy boldnes. I may compare thee to Sidrack, Miſack, and Abdenago, whych ra ther then they wold forſake their mayſter, were contented to ſuffer the tormentes in the hoate bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ouen. And as young Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el when he was broughte before ſuch a ruler (as that falſe Duke of Northumberland) rather then to denye his Lord, would ſuffer the paynes of impryſonment, and to be caſt in the denne of lions. Euen ſo (faythful Gilbard) rather then thou wouldeſte conſente to their falſe &amp; trayterouſe proclamation
<pb facs="tcp:508:5"/>
for Iane, when thou dyd heare it, hauyng a cleare conſcience, wold not conſent to the ſame moſt trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous fact. And ſo litle regarded thy life, boldly ſtode in thy miſtres cauſe, and offered thy bodye to be inpriſoned, &amp; to ſuffer death, then to denye our vertuouſe Mary to be quene. And therfore truſt to it, (my faythful Gilbard) as the god of Sidrack, Miſack, &amp; Abdenago ſaued them from al hurt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoat burnyng ouen, that not ſo muche as one heare of their heade was peryſhed. So ſhall the ſame God ſaue thee out of the handes of the cruell beare, and gyue hym no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of thy lyfe. Agayne as God preſerued Daniel when he was caſt in the denne amongeſt the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the king Nabuchodonoſor. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was in the middeſte of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the lions playd with him (which was
<pb facs="tcp:508:5"/>
admirable). So do thou truſt to, albeit thou art now in the denne amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt deuourers (I meane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of the beare &amp; the raged ſtaf) yet the god of Daniel ſhall ſafely delyuer thee out of all their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, &amp; thee rather, if thou doſt ſtil continue ſtedfaſt and hold on Mary our quene, and forſake thy mayſter, no more then Daniel &amp; the brethren did their God and mayſter. Diſpayre not, but lyue in hope to ſe a good day, &amp; the ſoner wil it come, it we continue in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. For my part, faithful Gylbard, I wyl neuer ſeaſe day nor nyght from praying for our good Mary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her grace mighte once obteyne the crowne, &amp; that it wold pleaſe him of his omnipotente power to ſtrengten &amp; helpe her grace, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thy Quene &amp; mine, ſo ſaye I to the death, &amp; to conquere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beare. So here I ſhall deſire thee alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:508:6"/>
offer vp to the almighty lord, god ly contemplations, that ſhe maye ouercome her enemies.</p>
            <p>For as the inhabitours of the great city of Niniue continued in prayer, &amp; clothed them ſelues in ſackecloth, caſte duſte vpon their heades, repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, &amp; bewailed their manifold ſinnes and offences, at what tyme as the Prophete Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas had preached to them the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their citye, knew that it was time to do all the ſame, els deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold folow. So ſhulde we now not ceaſe praying to God to ſend vs quietnes, &amp; that the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mary might enioye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>For we haue had manye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes &amp; true preachers whiche did declare vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oure kinge ſhalbe taken awaye from vs, &amp; a tirant ſhal reygne, the Goſpel ſhal be plucked awaye, the right heyre ſhalbe diſpoſſeſſed, &amp; al for our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanckfulnes,
<pb facs="tcp:508:6"/>
&amp; thinkeſt thou not (Gilbard) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world is now come? Yea truely. And what ſhal folow yf we repente not in tymes. The ſame God wil take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe Lady Mary oure lawfull quene, &amp; ſend ſuch a cruel Pharao as the ragged beare, to rule vs, which ſhal pul &amp; pol vs, ſpoyle vs, &amp; vtterly deſtroy vs, &amp; bringe vs in great calamities and miſeries. And this god wil ſend vs, &amp; all for our iniquities. For yf vnto oure quene Mary any euell ſhuld hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let vs fully perſwade with our ſelues, that it is not for her ſmall ſinnes only, but for our euel liuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And this litle troubles (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be greuous to hir grace) doth chaunſe to her for thy ſinnes and myne, let vs ſo thinke. For truely (faythful Gilbard) god is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs many wayes. And here I dar be bold to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her grace is
<pb facs="tcp:508:7"/>
more ſorowful for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of king Edwarde her brother, then ſhe is glad y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe is quene. For her parte (good vertuouſe lady) ſhe would haue bene as glad of her brothers life, as the ragged beare is glad of his death. <hi>Agamenon</hi> the heathen king was neuer more vnquieted with his highe eſtate, when he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for that he was king ouer ſo manye people, as her grace is nowe troubled to rule &amp; gouerne ſo manye euell perſons. <hi>Plato</hi> was neuer gladder, when he was exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kinges courte, becauſe his mind was more addict therby and geuen to the ſtudy of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, as ſhe wold be, if ſhe might once be exiled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the company of ſuch traitours, wherby ſhe might be more quieter, and poſſeſſe this her kingdome peaſablye. Euen ſo I dare aduouche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her grace was farre quieter, &amp; better contented
<pb facs="tcp:508:7"/>
with her olde eſtate, then now ſhe is quene (yf it had pleaſed God) But now praiſed be almighti god becauſe he hath ſo prouided vs a right &amp; lawful ayre, &amp; ſo vertuous a princeſſe, to poſſeſſe this imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al crowne of England, &amp; ſo are we all bounde highlye to thanke him therfore. Truſtyng that the ſame god wil ſhortlye exalt her grace, &amp; ſet her in her perfect dignitie, and plucke downe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iane, I can not nominate hir quene, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I know no other quenes, but the good la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mary her grace, whome God proſper. I heare ſay (faithful Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true ſubiect ſir Edmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d peckhame is gone with al his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; treaſure to aſſiſt her grace. <hi>Ex fructu ſcimus quid ſit arbor,</hi> By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute we may knowe what the tree is. So by his frutes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, by al his do inges we may knowe, what he is, howe true &amp; faythful hath he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb facs="tcp:508:8"/>
him ſelfe to be at all times to Henry theight of famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. What man deſerued more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation then he? He neuer rob bed his grace, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had all the rule of his treaſure, he vſed not to bye ſiluer for foure ſhillinges an once &amp; made the kinge paye fiue ſhillinges fowre pence (as other falſe traitours did) but loke what he payd, the king payde no more. He was euer true &amp; faithful by re porte aſwell of all other as of hys owne ſeruauntes. And now for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful triall of his true hearte, howe hath he ſhowed him ſelfe to her grace, left houſe landes &amp; al, and gone to help her. Truly we haue to few ſuch faithful men. I heare alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is come more to helpe her grace, the Erle of Darbey, the Erle of Oxford, the Erle of Bath, &amp; diuerſe other nobles, whiche I can not rehearſe nominatly. The
<pb facs="tcp:508:8"/>
God of hoſtes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God of Abraham proſper them, kepe them, &amp; geue them power to withſtand al their enemies, &amp; the mooſt mighty lord take part with them (as I do not miſtruſt) for the right ſake. I hear no other newes, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here is con tinually great preparation, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cartes appoynted to cary har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; artilery, God ſend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euell to ſpede. The good Erle of Arun del, and the Erle of Shroſburye be here ſtil, but as I am informed, the Erle of Arundel will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to none of their doynges. O God I moſt hertelye deſire thee, heare my prayer, kepe &amp; preſerue the good Erle of Arundel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deuouryng beare. For as thou haſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning en dued him with al truth, ſo doth he ſtil continue ſtedfaſt in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame, like a worthy noble, preſerue him I be ſeche thee (o my god) &amp; geue hym
<pb facs="tcp:508:9"/>
grace ſtill to ſtande ſtedfaſte. The Erle of Shroſbury beareth hym ſelfe equal god kepe him, &amp; ſend al thoſe that wold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ladye Mary to be quene long life &amp; pleaſure, and they which wold not, I wyſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the paynes of Satan in hell. I haue (faithfull Gilbard) ſcattered abroad thre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes more, and two alſo haue I ſent into the rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged beares campe, kepe that cloſe which thou haſt: the world is dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gerous: the great deuell Dudley ruleth, Duke I ſhuld haue ſayde, wel let y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paſſe, ſeing it is oute, but I truſte he ſhal not longe. I haue proued if I could get a. M. of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in printed in ſome ſtraunge letter &amp; ſo a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be diſparſed abroade. Foraſmuch (Gilbard) as I perceaue that thou art ſtraytly kept, &amp; not ſuffred to haue liberty I ſhal brieuely viſite the with my letters fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time. And here
<pb facs="tcp:508:9"/>
Gilbard I exhort the to continue in prayer, &amp; to take in good parte this yoke, layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſhoulders &amp; beare this croſſe patiently. For aduerſity is a good thinge, &amp; ſhall make thee to know god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better. For I truſt in the lord to liue to ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day her grace to mary ſuch one, as knoweth what aduerſity mea neth, ſo ſhal we haue both a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful quene &amp; king to their ſubiects. And wold to god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might liue (if it ſo pleaſed her grace) to haue an other vertuouſe Edward: &amp; God make her grace frutful, &amp; ſend her frute to inherite the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after her. I promiſed you to ſalut your frend Robert in your name, accor dingly I haue done, deſired hym to pray w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you for our quene Ma ry, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wold pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde to giue her the crowne, which ſhe oughte to haue of right. And thus to bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiate my long proceſſe I end, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:508:10"/>
the (my conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Gilbard) not to beholde the gorgiouſnes of my letters, which be void of al, but to weygh in an equal payre of balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the good wil of the writer, who beareth the no worſe wil, then to his owne ſoule, prayinge God to ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, &amp; geue thee grace, to abide faythfull tow<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ardes oure moſt excellent true &amp; onlye quene Mary, ſo ſhalt thou be aſſured to haue god thy faithful fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againe, &amp; at the laſt thou ſhalt inherit his kingdom: to the which kingdome bringe both you &amp; me, and vs all.</p>
            <closer>Amen</closer>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fayre you well.</salute>
               <signed>Quod Poore Pratte.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprynted at London in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrete ouer agaynſte the Stiliar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, at the ſigne of the dobbel hood, by Hewghe Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelton.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:508:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
